this episode is once again an effort to
combine a concept that's already been
articulated in this case in the medium
post with the medium of video YouTube -
hopefully elucidate the concept more
effectively
this concept is sovereignty and of
course I'll go into some detail about
what I mean by that in a moment
but those of you who want to delve more
deeply into that concept I will into
medium post below so the idea is that we
can reconcile as this concept of
sovereignty using a new framework and
the point is that I think that this new
framework is a good deep way of
anchoring sovereignty in a more
foundational fashion that is appropriate
to the set of problems that we face
today and in point of fact I use this
concept often involved probably quite
likely referred to it in other other
videos so it's effectively a triadic
structure the notion is there's three
distinct underlying capacities that are
associated with to be sovereign and also
that your sovereignty then represents a
sort of general purpose capacity to
respond to the world so that's the
simplest sense of what it means so to
say that you are our sovereign is to say
that within a certain context and in a
certain set of circumstances you have
the capacity to take responsibility for
your circumstances to respond to the
environmental generator as opposed to
city overwhelmed by it or so you going
to react to it etc so this is the core
notion but we can actually decompose
that and then reconfigure it and bring
it back together in a way that I think
is very powerful very timely in a
contemporary environment for those of
you who are familiar with Boyd's new
Duluth which is four points observe
orient decide act you can kind of
imagine the three that I'm describing as
being the blank space in between and
maybe I'll reference that it's because
through it so the first aspect of
sovereignty is is perception the
capacity to receive information from
your environment and this particular
capacity has three primary
characteristics one you might think of
as being the modalities of perception so
for example
vision is a different modality than
smell looks was different modality than
hearing and this distinction modality is
very important because different
modalities of perception have very
different qualities there are things
that you can see that you cannot hear
and things you can hear that you cannot
see no matter how how much acuity your
vision your hearing happen to have and
the fact that the reality happens to be
partitioned to that way is actually
quite interesting but in any event
modality and the number of modalities
with which you go about perceiving is a
fundamental characteristic of your
underlying capacitive perception another
one though is bandwidth so so bandwidth
has to do with the amount of information
flow you can actually receive through a
given modality so this is both in terms
of the continuum of the total
possibilities so within the
electromagnetic spectrum for example but
what portion of that spectrum can you
see and then also the velocity the
actual amount of information flow is
coming out to that you could process
effectively at least 3 perceptual lens
and then the last characteristic is
subtlety or discernment in perception
and this has to do with the ability to
not just perceive kind of raw bandwidth
maybe a little bit of a distinction
between say a telescope and a microscope
where a telescope has a capacity to have
subtlety in the direction of distance a
microscope has the capacity of something
in the direction of the very small and
so those are obviously two very very
different capacities within what may be
the same bandwidth in the same room down
on the vision and then all of this
perceptions in the context of overwhelm
because while your instruments of
perception have certain capacities to
perceive they also have certain
thresholds after which the capacity is
selflessly crazy so you've got sort of
an upper limit of what you can perceive
but then you also have a degree to which
signals outside of that limit actually
degraded capacity so if you listen to a
loud noise you then lose your hearing a
capacity for some period of time or a
flash of light makes it harder to see
for some period of time and so
that agreed to it you were able to
increase modality increase bandwidth
increase subtlety and increase your
capacity to perceive without being
overwhelmed you then increase this
dimension of Socrates's the precession
dimension of sovereignty and then you
have the the second dimension which is
the dimension perhaps of processing or
intelligence and the handoff between the
two is the dimension of sense making and
so in the second category we're talking
about an ability to take perception to
convert it into meaning and again this
has number of characteristics you have
things like your RAW processing speed
how much information can you take in and
convert it maybe that you're getting
overwhelmed at the level of intelligence
not at the level of perception but also
other things that map a little bit to
modality and bandwidth and subtlety for
example your capacity to develop
frameworks of that abstraction so that
you can actually take large amounts of
raw information and decompose it into
structures and patterns and models you
model incapacity is a component of of
intelligence or processing and then
pattern recognition you're deleted to
notice and detect pattern because you
even compress and use as objects that
you can plug into your model so these
are all aspects of intelligence and and
that's also important to recognize the
feedback between the two modes or the
two domains so you have a inclusive
level if you have a hearing and vision
modality of perception you're going to
need to have a hearing and vision
processing capacity and then also
broadly speaking you'll need to have a
binding capacity which is to to compare
the inputs from those two different
modes and convert them into some bound
model of the reality in which you're
operating that takes advantage of the
parallax of comparison and then then the
other side of the intelligence capacity
is going from making sense of your
environment to making meaning every
environment
or to making choices and this is the
Boyd model is it the decide side of the
equation so here what's happening is
you're not comparing the input what the
environment is telling me what's going
on two possible outputs and then this of
course is largely both modeling your own
state which your portfolio of possible
actions what can you do viable and then
sort of a sense of what might be
effective in your environment your
strategy and planning and then this this
boundary condition and connects to the
third capacity which is properly
speaking your your capacity to actually
act here your genetic capacity per se so
this is going to clean the portfolio of
actions that you have available to you
can you walk and you talk can you write
software code the efficiency with which
you can project your will into the world
meeting it with the ratio of effect to
energy is it very very difficult you
spend a lot of energy getting a small
effect or can you deliver on the effect
that you desire with a very small amount
of energy but also for example the
ability to avoid unintended consequences
are you a bull in a china shop
are you delivering what you want but
also delivering a whole lot of things
that you don't want and the combination
of these different characteristics and
so that that sum total ends up being
your your action capacity or your or
Gentek portion of this triad so your
perception you have intelligence and you
have agency and notice the wall the
priory flow or the dominant flow is from
perception through to agency and then of
course it goes into environment you do
stuff but it causes the environment to
change in some way and then you can see
what happens and your honor
loop which is now both the Boyd Buddha
loop and the sovereignty loop in the way
that I'm describing it now also there is
gonna go see another way that we at
least and I think most sentient
creatures will have a dispositional
attitude so for example if you are
disposed towards being in a fight let's
say for example you're already
perceive that you may be in a fight your
body's not prepared to be in a fight
you're actually feeding back from your
action potential into your twist making
and meaning making all the way down to
perception so you'll actually be
potentially more likely to perceive
threats and less likely to perceive
things that are non threats because your
dispositional attitude that the action
level is actually feeding back into the
circle so there's there's forward and
backwards loops in sovereignty okay so
that's that's the framework kind of
theoretical level and so there's a
couple of things one is we can speak
about sovereignty now as almost well not
as almost as a capacity which means that
there's a continuum you can have a
certain level of sovereignty it'll have
certain qualities and this will measure
your ability to respond to your
environment so I may be sovereign now
under the conditions that I am in under
this roof sets of things to which I must
respond but I might find myself not
sovereign something may have come that
is outside of metrosexual capacity or I
might have been overwhelmed and overall
capacity degraded the second thing is
that we can notice how this concept
relates to some of the other things that
are going on in the broader world so a
hypothesis or heuristic
might be that one should always only act
in one of two ways either within the
scope of your sovereignty or to upgrade
or improve your sovereignty itself so if
you find yourself faced with the
potential problem some tasks some
challenge either you are up to the
challenge or your sovereignty is able to
respond to what's happening or you
should actually focus first and foremost
on getting your sovereignty up to the
task which means for example that as a
heuristic if you're faced with the
challenge that is outside the scope of
your sovereignty venturing into that
challenge is only a worst-case scenario
choice what you should instead do is
improve her increase your sovereignty so
that then you're able to respond to your
environment
what here might be saying like at a
sporting event if you don't know how to
shoot an arrow at all you're not going
to do very well in an archery
competition and so then rather than just
sort of why are we shooting and missing
the right response is just to upgrade
your capacity become more skillful and
that particular endeavor and we can
extend this broadly so for example
Jordan Peterson I was in ado saying this
medium pose is in many ways just
pointing this fact out that sovereignty
is the place from which you have the
ability to be responsible and you have
an obligation to be responsible for me
you can be responsible for but it's
actually in fact foolishness to endeavor
to be responsive outside of your ability
to respond so first and foremost figure
out what your sovereignty is so begin in
the middle beginning in the center
beginning with you you clean your room
if you can't take care of something like
that then what makes you think that you
have prepared to take care of something
even more complex so start with yourself
get yourself sorted out get yourself in
a space of self sovereignty and build
things like you know awareness of your
capacities and how your capacities are
operating now am i overwhelmed am i
working effectively in my own flow
around the loop and then build a
learning crawler I build the commitment
the ability to build capacity then build
discernment which is the relationship
between the capacity components and how
to actually notice where you are in
relationship to your capacity to learn
and your capacity then finally to
respond and as you have gone to that
process as you've actually mastered
sovereignty itself then you are in fact
optimally positioned to go out into the
world and do begin to address more broad
and maybe more significant or more in
principle meaningful challenges so
that's so that's it that's this
particular concept I will in fact likely
be referring to some sub components of
this concept in the future so if it
doesn't make
sense it might make be a good idea to
take a look at the media post maybe
writing is a is something over which you
have more Socrates if they're for sexual
modality and of course I've spent more
time on it did this video which I once
again have done off the top of my head
by the way
for those of you have been noting that
you'd like to see audio quality and when
had made investment and bought this
Elvis style microphone so I hope the
audio quality is up to standard if it is
I'll get a stand so I don't have to hold
it Elvis style and they eventually
agreed my recording capacity in general